hello and welcome back to another video
with it's Dr Dan and today we're going
to be looking at precipitation reactions
which more specifically occur in aqueous
Solutions so in the liquid phase so when
it comes to looking at these what
exactly do we need to remember what do
we need to know
so the first thing is we have to be
aware of how different
solutes behave in salt in the solvent of
water meaning that if we're looking at
different aqueous Solutions where the
solvent is water what exactly happens
when are they mixed in is it something
that is soluble meaning that it breaks
into its ions therefore leaving it open
for reaction or is it something that is
insoluble that separates from the
individual solution and actually makes a
solid as a result so that's what we're
going to be trying to look at here is is
something going to be a solid or is it
going to be aqueous going through those
two individual types of reactions here
so when we have two two different
solutions what can happen is we are
always trying to figure out what is the
actual chemistry within a reaction can
we illustrate it because in a lot of
double replacement reactions you have
multiple Solutions mixing together and
it's not always obvious where the actual
chemistry is occurring sure you mix
these things together but you have
multiple ions that are participating in
the reaction so how can we show that
well precipitation reactions you will
see a solid form so and that's from when
you mix two aqueous reaction or two
aqueous Solutions so one of the things
that we're going to be looking at is all
right well if we have let's say these
two individual vials here even though
they're both aqueous when they are
separated well what happens when you mix
them together let's say we put them in
the same test tube is it going to
precipitate out and sometimes you're
going to see that you might have a
solution that are completely clear then
all of a sudden like magic just like in
the instant you have a solid that forms
so that's something that we're going to
be looking at step by step on how we can
see these so how do we do that how do we
do these kind of problems
[Music]
so the very first thing that we're going
to do is if I have the following problem
here below
so it says we have iron III nitrate and
sodium hydroxide so I have here drawn um
I have iron three nitrate drawn on the
left and you see that it's dissolved
notice how the ions are apart and then
we also have sodium hydroxide over here
where the hydroxides are separated from
the sodiums
they completely dissolve in water what
will be the net ionic equation if you
mix them in an aqueous solution
all right what what does that mean so
what we're going to be doing is step by
step on how to get to net ionic
equations
so if we have a net ionic equation how
do we show it so let's
let's try to go about doing that so the
very first thing we need to do is write
out and convert the names here so
looking at this reaction we have iron
III nitrate and the sodium hydroxide
these are the two things mixing together
so if we remember from naming we have f
e for iron it has a Roman numeral three
so that tells you that it has a charge
of three plus
nitrate is one of our polyatomic ions so
that's going to be NO3 minus
we have to being that these are separate
ions we have to swap drop them
so if we do that we swap drop or
numerical values this is going to lead
to us having
Fe
with a nitrate on the other side
with three individual nitrates all
around iron
now the other one is sodium hydroxide
so so this is going to be an addition to
sodium
hydroxide and what we're going to be
seeing is how did they actually react
together
so this is our reaction and what we're
going to do is step by step how can we
do that so first step predict get the
names sometimes you don't always need
that step but sometimes we have to it
depends on the difficulty of the problem
the harder problems are going to make
you do that the easier ones not so much
all right now let's predict the products
so with most aqueous reactions it's
going to be double replacement or double
displacement reactions about 99 of them
which is really nice that means we don't
have to try to play this guessing game
of what is the recipe for figuring out
what type of chemical reactions so we
have the following right we had iron
nitrate
and that is mixing with sodium hydroxide
here
and this is going to be a double
replacement reaction
so being that is the case we're going to
do a B plus CD so we'll label our
species so every cation and anion gets a
label so iron would be one nitrate would
be the other
sodium is one hydroxide is the other
so being that the tip here is inside
outside
the inside bond together
and then the outside on together
so what exactly would we get now being
that we have to predict the products in
this type of reaction
we have to make sure we are writing down
what ions we are creating we're only
looking at the ions
so
being that we'll have iron
3 plus that's going to be mixing with
hydroxide
o h minus and then we're also going to
have sodium
Plus
and nitrate minus mixing together so
these are going to be our parts here
so we predicted the reaction we have our
products but are we finished here so our
next step is we have to do the swap drop
on all of our products it's only the
individual ions that are mixing together
in solution here so what we're going to
be checking is is all right well if I
have my first one here so we'll just
write them down here we have Fe 3 plus
oh minus
we'll take the 3 cross it the one cross
it
so what we're going to end up getting is
iron with just one single iron mixed
with three ohs
to balance out the iron so the whole
idea here is that we have a three plus
and then three individual one minuses to
balance out both sides of that reaction
now let's try the same thing on the
other one so on the other side we have n
a plus
with nitrate NO3 minus notice how the
same thing here is we have a plus one
minus one it's already balanced we don't
have to do anything else with it we
actually do not have to swap drop this
one being that it is a plus one and a
minus one charges they are balanced
in terms of charges so let's fill all
that in so we had
feoh and it has a 3 next to it and then
the nano3
now the next step mentions to go through
and balance it so if we're going to
balance our reaction here
one thing we have to double check is
looking at all of other different
species that we have here do we have the
correct
amount of polyatomics of
of individual ions is it balanced so one
of the big tricks is here is let's start
with the polyatomics so one thing you're
going to see is that on the left hand
side of the reaction
we have
three nitrates on the left
one nitrate on the right
so how can we go through and easily
balance that well we got to add
subscripts
so if I go through and put a subscript
on the right hand side next to sodium
this is going to multiply my number of
nitrates by three
therefore causing my nitrates to be
balanced now in the process it also
takes it and multiplies my sodiums by
three as well so there's three sodiums
on the right hand side
and there's only one sodium on the left
so how can we try to zigzag going back
and forth
we can put a 3 on the left side to
balance that
as a result that also adds three ohs
which it's already balanced on the right
hand side and one thing you'll see Iron
spell too
so we have to do many different steps in
this reaction we have to predict it
write out our ions and balance it to try
to go through our reaction
all right
the next step in our process here is to
actually use the solubility table to
determine what is soluble
what is insoluble so
when we do that this is actually going
to allow us to
um write out all of our
different
pieces that we have so if we have our
equation here why don't we rewrite it
for ourselves we'll clean it up
so we have f e n o three
now in the original problem it told us
this was soluble so that means that this
is already
aqueous in that case
then we also had that we had three NaOH
that was also aqueous
and then we that was mixing with f e
o H3 we need to look up the solubility
of that and then 3 and a n o three
so let's take a look and see what is
soluble what is not using the solubility
rules so we got to take a look at our
original equations and try to identify
what is so in the in the both
ingredients we have iron hydroxide
if this is soluble in water so go to my
previous video showing solubility
this would make fe3 Plus
with three o h minus
the other species would be n a n O3
if mixed with water would make sodium
and nitrate so let's look at the first
one
is iron or hydroxide are they soluble
so when we're looking at these tables we
need to find look for the common ions
hydroxide is a very normal polyatomic
one thing you see that it's right down
here at the bottom it's something that
is insoluble for most compounds except
when it's bound to calcium barium
strontium
this case it's bound to iron so this is
an insoluble reaction so this would not
actually form here we would not get
these ions so this is going to be
insoluble
so we'll write that here meaning that
iron hydroxide is going to be a solid so
we'll write a little s next to that to
tell you that this is a solid
sodium nitrate on the other hand this
actually goes under our Anna
abbreviation
meaning that both of them alkali metals
are always soluble no matter what
um so we can see that here and so are
nitrates they're both soluble all the
time so in this case these are aqueous
so we can actually
show that these are going to be making
ions
so this would be our answer here for
release for this and what this is called
is our complete
molecular equation is what we have up
above so we're labeling all the
different states so you have to label
the how what label the states
balance it go through all the different
pieces that is what this is called that
is a complete molecular equation perfect
however it was asking for the net ionic
equation so how do we get there let's
copy and paste what we have here and go
to our next
step
all right the next step
five so with this the whole idea
was is all right if we take
this we need to see what dissociates
between the reactants and the products
meaning what actually makes ions so from
before one thing that we could actually
see here was is that okay well we had
all of these different
uh everything on the left hand side was
aqueous so they're all going to break
down into ions and then we have all of
the products most of them will break it
down into ions as well except for
anything as a precipitate or a solid and
a gas so we're going to write down all
of the ions so on the left hand side
iron nitrate breaks down into iron three
plus
and the three nitrates
then we'll also have sodium hydroxide so
we have three sodiums
three hydroxides notice how I'm carrying
out the coefficients here so being that
we had a coefficient of 3 for sodium
that gets carried out across the entire
thing but it's dissociating right there
all three of those molecules the same
hydroxide are breaking apart
so
the next one is iron hydroxide so when
that breaks apart that we found that
that was a precipitate so that stays it
stays as f e o h three and that's going
to stay as a solid
all of these other species on the left
hand side
these are all going to be aqueous and
for most chemistry classes you have to
label that is AQ
um to show that it is dissociating
then we have three na Plus
and three
nitrates and both of these are also
aqueous as well okay so both those have
your AQ next to them
to show those are breaking apart
now are we done so what this is now has
a name too this is the complete
ionic equations so this is showing what
is an ion what is a precipitate in our
formula and really the thing that we're
trying to figure out is really what is
the reaction occurring one thing you're
probably going to take note of is it's
going to have something to do with the
formation of this iron itself how can we
actually form this so this is a complete
ionic equation
now the idea is here is what we now want
to do is our final step is write out the
net ionic equation so how do we do that
so the way to show that is by canceling
out spectator ions so what is a
spectator well if you go to a sporting
event we are spectators we are not
participating in the actual event we are
just watching we're not actually doing
anything we're just enjoying it so what
would be happening here is if you have
spectators
so what we do is we look at both sides
of the reaction and see where are their
Spectators for example notice how there
are three nitrates on the left hand side
three on the right it's on both sides of
the creation so cancel out
same ions and it has to be an ion in an
individual ion too
and it has to be both sides there's one
other
individual ion that you might see and
that is if we see n a plus right that's
on the left and also on the right so
that goes away now the net ionic
equation is whatever is left over
so the net ionic
and in this case we have
fe3 Plus
aqueous
plus three hydroxide
also aqueous yields the precipitate
f e o h three and that is a solid
and that is our final answer
in this problem so that is our net ionic
equation in this particular reaction so
we had to do a lot of work it takes all
your former skills to really go through
it and try to figure out what is your
net ionic reaction
so
what if just one quick little example
what if you had the following so here I
have sodium nitrate and sodium or sorry
an ammonium chloride reacting together
notice how both of these species are
everything here is something that is
soluble meaning that these are both
aqueous they follow our Anna rule so
Anna is alkali metals
uh so we have our alkali metals here so
this follows it nitrate follows it
ammonium follows it they're always
soluble
if this is to happen where you have an
example where if we do inside outside
meaning that both of the products are
completely soluble so if this is to
break down into all of its ions
when we write the ionic equation
what is the what is the answer in terms
of this reaction
well being that everything here
is an ion everything cancels out
so if that's the case well all of your
individual ions decide to cancel out
completely so all the chlorines are
canceling all of the sodiums are
canceling all the ammoniums are
canceling when that actually happens
well that is when
we have a complete no reaction
okay so whenever everything is soluble
that means that no reaction actually
occurred there has to be something
formed so in order for a reaction we
must either have a precipitation
reaction
or you have to have a gas Evolution
something needs to happen in the
reaction so keep that in mind you can
have it where everything is soluble and
it all cancels out
so this is my video on how to do net
ionic equations I hope that this helped
um please feel free to hit that like And
subscribe button I hope to see you all
for future videos and thank you all so
much for supporting the channel and more
videos to come and that's how I try to
improve in making these better all right
I'll see you all later and have a
wonderful day
foreign